[Music]
know
hi this is robert here with another
edition of sheer intelligence where the
intelligence comes from my guests and
my goodness no one can fit that bill
better than john kiriakou
who
first of all in terms of languages knows
arabic knows greek uh and a few others
was a ci agent for quite a long time i
guess about 12 how many years was it
john 15 years 15 years
was one of those people out in the field
he was involved in the capture of what
was alleged then to be the third most
important operative in al qaeda and he
refused to go along with the torture
program turn down the training and then
is actually the only person uh connected
with the torture program who served any
uh
penalty criminal penalty uh served two
years for they said revealing the name
of a cia agent it's a whole other story
we've covered it before
but it was not even a closet agent but
the reason i wanted to talk to john this
week
is that he accompanied uh as a
journalist uh president biden on his
historic trip to saudi arabia and the
question i really want to begin with is
your whole life you were recruited right
out of graduate school by the cia by one
of your professors and your whole life
was built around stopping uh terrorism
in the form of arab uh extremism
and
it was all triggered by the attack of 9
11 in which 15 of the 19 hijackers was
from saudi arabia and you were involved
in sort of defending the country now of
course we've got our old enemy of russia
back and here was the president going
over to make nice
with the uh crown prince
and apparent heir to power in saudi
arabia how did it feel how did it feel
first of all being there as a member of
the press
and
what was your return like and then tell
us about this really frightening
political moment and what the president
accomplished or didn't accomplish
wow all very good questions um you know
it's it's
[Music]
there's a there's a dramatic difference
between
going to some place like saudi arabia as
a cia officer undercover and going to
saudi arabia as a journalist
when you go as a cia officer you have an
enormous invisible network of support
you have
weapons if you need them you have
surveillance teams and counter
surveillance teams if you need them to
keep you safe
uh you've got armored
vehicles
uh you know it's you're never alone
you're never alone when you're overseas
with the cia you always have a team
behind you even if no one else can see
that team
when you go as a journalist
uh that's the definition of being alone
my job was to go
and cover the president's uh trip i had
to make all of the arrangements uh on my
own i had to get my press credentials on
my own i was shocked frankly to even get
press credentials and the only
conclusion i could draw was that
the person in the white house press
office
was so young that he or she probably
didn't know what sputnik was
and so uh i got my press credentials uh
i wish i mentioned that you have been
doing a radio program on sputnik correct
both before uh the russian invasion of
ukraine after and we've discussed that
but you you are on the area not a very
big station no uh and uh full disclosure
you also were writing a couple of
columns for me at sharepost so i was
very worried did i send you to your
death
and you wrote some pretty tough critical
columns which you filed from saudi
arabia and you talked about the crown
prince as a murderer as a murderer held
him responsible right for murder
you know you weren't any doubt yeah and
president the president didn't say
anything publicly he claims he raised it
privately but the fact is he was there
to forgive the crown prince that's right
and once again
forgive saudi arabia for anything nobody
even brings up 9 11. uh and uh yes and
so you were in this odd position
and
tell us about it and you know i i'm glad
that you brought that up too because i
decided many years ago
that
i can only tell the truth right i'm i'm
sort of viewed as as a whistleblower
because of the cia's torture program i
did that because i made a decision in
2007 to tell the truth to a journalist
who asked me tough questions and you
know i want to be able to sleep at night
i'm proud of what i write and what i
write about and it's it's got to be
based on truth
and so
i know you and i joked before i i left
for saudi arabia about um
about well maybe it was a half a joke
about
gallows humor yeah
that's right i was worried about i mean
they killed a washington post columnist
right
why wouldn't they kill a sugarpost
columnist yeah right and so i was i was
careful about my own security i was
cognizant of of the possibility of being
followed and then when i'm sitting there
in the hotel room with my computer when
i sat down to start writing the piece i
thought you know
i know i'm in saudi arabia i know
i'm at their mercy
but i've got to tell the truth and
just before i had arrived in jeddah
the uh the british newspaper the
independent had published an article
saying that a saudi intelligence source
had told them
that in 2014 crown prince mohammed bin
salman had broached the the idea of
assassinating king abdullah so that his
own father
the current king salman could become
king sooner
well that's
i mean you you can't get any more
inflammatory than that
and so this this accusation was
perfectly in keeping with muhammad bin
salman's personality i believe him to be
a sociopath
and
and we know what he did to the
washington post journalist jamal
khashoggi not just had him murdered but
uh but had him dismembered chopped up
there are recordings of him screaming as
they're cutting his arms off
and then disposed of his body we don't
know where we've heard reports that it's
in a well somewhere in in greater
istanbul
so there's no sense in trying to
sugarcoat this uh president biden
actually before he was president when he
was running for president uh in the in
the 2020 primaries
said that mohammed bin salman was a
murderer and that the saudi regime had
no
socially redeeming qualities those are
very very tough words
and i'll tell you i i enjoyed hearing
an important person in american
political life say such a thing
because
we're all taught
that the united states and saudi arabia
have had what's called a special
relationship since the 1930s since
the the franklin roosevelt
administration and roosevelt's trip to
saudi arabia in 1936
where he met with ibn saud the first
king of saudi arabia king abdulaziz
the current king's father and uh
and that special relationship is uh is
just simply not true
the truth is
we need each other even if we don't like
each other
we buy saudi oil and the saudis buy
american weaponry and that's really the
extent of the relationship it doesn't go
much beyond that and and let me let me
add to that too we keep them in power
though yeah we do we do because we have
military installations there and uh and
we need that constant flow of oil and
and they buy so much in the way of
weapons and weapon systems that it keeps
the american economy going when i when i
arrived in saudi arabia for the very
first time in 1990 it was just after
iraq had invaded kuwait in august of
i was so excited to be there because it
was my first overseas trip as a cia
officer and i had a small apartment in
the diplomatic corridor not far from the
american embassy so i would walk from my
apartment to the embassy every morning
and i'd go into the back gate
which was sort of the employee gate and
there was a saudi policeman standing
guard there every day and
my very first day i smiled at him and i
said salamu alaikum may peace be upon
you and the traditional response of
course is
salaam and upon you peace
so i said to him
salaamwalekum and he looked at me and
just ignored me and i thought wow that
was odd and rude but okay
so the next day i went to work again
eight o'clock and i said salaamu alaikum
and again he ignored me
and then the third day i said for the
third time salaamu alaikum and he
ignored me and i said what's your
problem
how would you say it in arabic
and he said
and he says to me in english he said you
are hired help
we paid for you to come here to protect
the oil fields we are not friends
and that was like a slap in my face but
i came to realize in the intervening
months
that that's the attitude of most saudis
they look down on us we don't have their
kind of money we don't all drive
lamborghinis and ferraris and bugattis
we don't own giant houses in beverly
hills like they do or in knightsbridge
london
we're hired help for them
we go over there to work uh in the uh in
the oil companies we we run the oil
companies we sell them weapons
and that's it
we're not friends
so i hope they help us rearrange the mid
east so
uh that we keep power there that's right
you know that's right that they will do
but are they shifting what i got from
your columns is that actually biden came
back empty-handed he did and first of
all did he lie to us he said he did ra
and raised the question
of the
murder of
the washington post columnist but uh
one of the top aides
said no it was not brought up but even
if it had been brought up it was brought
up privately yes uh why are you bringing
up privately you're perfectly willing to
condemn well now putin or anybody else
uh uh z in china or anybody for all
kinds of crimes why would you not do it
publicly because you need the oil
you need the oil and you know i want to
believe my president i i want to believe
that that he did bring this up uh in the
meeting with muhammad bin salman now the
the aide that denied that the president
brought that up was al-jubeir and arnold
juber is a is a
you can't be any closer to the united
states and still be a saudi than adol
jubair
so
you know adol juber right now is the
minister of state for foreign affairs he
was a long-time saudi ambassador to the
united states
and he is a
a keen
observer and analyst of the american
political scene
so he's a believable guy
at the same time he works for muhammad
bin salman
so like i say
the only people in that room at the time
on the american side
were
were the president's uh note taker and
the national security adviser and the
ambassador the u.s ambassador to saudi
arabia so it was a classified meeting uh
the notes taken were classified there
was no press presence there
uh so that it's not going to appear in
the media you know the minutes of what
happened in this meeting so we have to
either believe the president or we
believe muhammad bin salman i'd like to
believe the president but i also wonder
bob
if the president went in there and said
look before we get to oil there's
something i need to get out of the way
we're really angry that you murdered
jamal khashoggi don't do that again you
put us in a very bad position
yeah but even whatever he said if you
don't say it publicly it has no force it
has no and for the articles that you
wrote for sure post let me get a plug in
here
you made it very clear that he came back
empty-handed yeah he did uh uh forget
the phrase you used that he was uh
taken right i i thought he was taken and
you know
two weeks before the president went to
saudi arabia uh french president
emmanuel macron called muhammad bin
salman and said look
we need oil and we need natural gas
because we're screwed here in western
europe which is true they're paying
eight nine ten dollars a gallon for gas
and mohammed bin salman told macron and
we know this because macron briefed the
media afterwards he told macron that
saudi arabia and the united arab
emirates are operating at full
production capacity and that they cannot
increase production now
mohammed bin salman said the day after
biden left saudi arabia that there's a
little bit of wiggle room
and they might be able to increase
production just a little bit
but they won't make that decision until
the opec plus meeting which is a month
from now
so joe biden went there with hat in hand
to ask the saudis the same saudis he's
criticized very harshly
uh to increase oil production and so far
we have nothing to show for it so i i
would call this visit of failure and and
i think that the visit was a big risk in
the first place i mean what were the
chances of success in the first place
it's gonna look like you're pandering
like you're begging after these things
that you said you've accused the crown
prince of murder i believe properly
but then at the same time you're going
to ask him to do you a favor
this is is is the reality
that we talk about freedom and our
respect for it and defending it and if
you really look at the whole just
certainly since world war ii when you go
back earlier uh
our allies have not lined up on the side
of freedom very often
and the pretense so now you know you
were involved and let's hunt down al
qaeda and everything uh now this some
a different song is being sung to the
people who are going to go have to fight
in ukraine or the ukrainians who are
dying that we care about freedom and
there's absolutely no evidence that has
ever driven driven our our foreign
policy there's absolutely no
correspondence to it and a perfect
example in other countries you know a
lot about egypt yes where you know
there was a situation where there was
the arab spring uh you know just as
there was you know
in eastern europe by the great uh
uh
moments and what happened uh
we said this is a victory for google and
our intelligence apparatus all of that
data got turned over to the military and
there are thousands of people now in
prison in egypt for having dared to
speak up and we cared we said about the
people involved in ukraine who spoke up
but suddenly we don't care about the
ones who spoke up in egypt and in fact
the president going over there was an
embrace of the most hardline
uh
authoritarian
power
in the arab world then by the way he
slighted the palestinians oh
yeah well let's talk a little bit about
this because you were a student of
foreign policy you were recruited into
the cia when you were a graduate student
you're a very smart fellow you've been
all around what is really driving all
this is the need
that we have for an enemy and we seize
one that's as we think is as attractive
as possible as a target or what what's
going on
give us the perspective of a veteran
yes um i do believe that i believe that
that we're as a country we're always
looking for an enemy
to rally against whether it's
socialism or communism or anarchism or
islamism uh whatever it is
we need
an enemy
and especially post 911
fighting those enemies even indirectly
is what keeps our economy going you know
there are more millionaires now per
capita in the washington dc area than
anywhere else in america including
silicon valley
that's not an accident
right that's because of the the military
industrial complex
but you've made a couple of very
important points here i'd like to uh to
comment on and and to reiterate in some
cases
egypt number one egypt is one of our
closest allies in the world
and the fact of the matter is that it's
a fascist dictatorship that's just the
way it is
and
while we talk a great game about human
rights and democracy and the rule of law
we don't really believe it
for other countries
you know i i say all the time too uh
when i when i give talks about human
rights
when i was serving in in bahrain which
is a small country in the persian gulf
it's just a little island it's connected
to saudi arabia by a long bridge and
it's about the same size and same
population as greater pittsburgh
so um
i was the human rights officer there and
as the human rights officer part of my
job was to um to investigate
human rights abuses in the country and
prepare an annual report for for
congress we do this with every country
in the world with which we have
diplomatic relations
and so i i would occasionally go to see
the minister of uh of interior who was
the prime minister's son-in-law and a
member of the royal family and i would
say your highness
you cannot beat to death a
fifteen-year-old boy because
he participated in a pro-democracy
demonstration you can't do that i have
to report this to congress i have to put
it in the human rights report
well
what do you think happens when i leave
the office
and then the cia station chief goes in
and says
don't listen to the human rights guy
we want you to put a secret prison here
where we can bring al qaeda prisoners
and we can torture them or you can
torture them and then you just give us a
report on what it is that they say
well he's not going to pay any attention
to the human rights guy
when the cia station chief is telling
him to do exactly the opposite
you know and this is something that adol
ju bear brought up in an interview
with the saudi press after biden left
he said uh he said biden says that he
wanted to talk about human rights and so
we said okay let's talk about human
rights at abu ghraib let's talk about
human rights at guantanamo and i hate to
say it bob but they have a point
and the point is that we're hypocrites
when it comes to these issues of human
rights
so again i hope the president raised the
murder of jamal khashoggi an innocent
man a member of the media who had done
nothing to hurt or harm anybody
at the same time we need to look at
ourselves
and the way we treat people time for a
break um we'll be back in a few minutes
we're back with sheer intelligence and
our guest
but we also have to look at the way
we're manipulated
and we're in yet another
period
where anybody who
disagrees in in in the most nuanced
way
with the dominant view of what's going
on in the ukraine oh yes or someone like
you who actually is on a radio station
uh sputnik which is russian owned right
uh
they're made of known person
okay
and uh and you were made a non-person
because you revealed the reality of
torture
only you were a premature
revealer of that we've had the senate
intelligence committee not that we can
read it in this great free society it's
still a heavily redacted intro that we
got to read parts of and we now have not
been able to see the whole report or any
of the report on torture you know and so
here was the saudi uh
leader saying what about what you do in
guantanamo what about what you did in
ebu grave and what is the answer the
answer is we believe when you
tear people apart and destroy them
physically and mentally it's not torture
if we do it that's right and that means
that every war we get involved with is
virtuous i mean we're doing it now you
know uh
the ukrainians have never done anything
wrong or who oppose putin right the ones
who support a russian presence or
support the russian language and so they
can't do anything right the only
civilian casualties that bother us are
people who are in the area that are
controlled by uh the anti-russian side
but if it's done in the done bus we
don't even have reports about it and
that has been the norm
in all of our wars we define
virtue there is not an independent
standard
of virtue which is after all our
constitution was an effort to establish
some independent standard of virtue and
governance
you know uh that has been mocked at
every turn
it has absolutely no significance
you're absolutely right you're
absolutely right it's always been like
this i mean just in our recent history
let's go back to the vietnam war
and look at look at what we did there
you know everything from the milai
massacre to the bombing of laos in
cambodia and everything that came
afterwards i mean we've never really
answered for any of that
but you're you're absolutely right
you know i take a lot of heat too
because i work uh for a russian outlet
and uh
well that's not your choice by the way
you when's the last time msnbc offered
you a job as a consultant i mean you
have been frozen out yes at the media
and you are genuinely an expert but the
experts that they want on are people who
looked the other way when torture was
being done you became a non person by
revealing torture that's right i i did i
did become a non-person i was for uh
let's see 2008 2009 and 2011 12 for four
years
i was a counter-terrorism
uh consultant and commentator for abc
news
and i'll tell you the first time i you
know you would work for the for john
kerry's committee right after i left abc
i went to john kerry
i was the chief investigator on the
senate foreign relations committee uh
but then
i was deemed to be too
controversial
right it was just too much controversy i
was the human rights guy it was too much
and i i've never been able to make a
professional recovery
but then at the same time with that said
i can sleep at night and uh
i'll tell you i got into a twitter fight
with the former deputy director of the
cia for operations a notorious torturer
by the name of jose rodriguez he was the
head of the counter-terrorism center and
he came up with a torture program it was
all his idea and um
when i got in trouble that actually was
the night before i left for prison
the new york times did an article about
me saying that you know i'm i'm headed
to prison
and he tweeted
at me
saying don't drop the soap oldest stupid
joke in the world
and
i wasn't going to respond i thought oh
it's better just to ignore him he's an
ignoramus and and it's just not worth it
and i thought about it and i said no i
am going to respond
and so what i said was
i'm proud of what i did
and i said jose
i'm on the right side of history and you
are not
and now he has to live
in a semi-secret location in florida
with private security and whatnot
because of what he did
you know
i'm proud of what i did i hope he's
proud of what he did too but most of
them don't live that way they have no
regrets yeah i i've interviewed a whole
bunch of these people over the years and
and the culture reaffirms
their torture reaffirms their violence
yes uh you know it was martin luther
king
who said you know how do i preach
non-violence to young kids in a ghetto
when my government is the major purveyor
of violence in the world today well
they never have recognized that when
they do it it's not violence that's
right you know it's interesting you
mentioned i i happened to go both south
to north vietnam and so forth i saw the
effects of american bombing and attack
and the anti-personnel weapons came into
their own in that war you know the
pineapple the guavas bombs the things
that sprayed out metal pellets you know
wounding and killing people and so forth
now when they're used in the russian
invasion of ukraine you know oh it's a
particularly heinous thing to do
we are the ones who made that a
respectable battlefield weapon right we
did that yes i mean it's stunning though
the hypocrisy and then there are plenty
of your former colleagues who are now
you know recycled as experts uh
particularly on msnbc and cnn
there's no accounting for their lives i
mean look the whole lies that got us
into the iraq war no accounting so i
just think you're being a bit charitable
uh
and you're just frankly and your
description of them
and clearly you'd rather be on on abc
than on sputnik because putnik is a
radio station that hardly reaches anyone
yeah you know what as part of our
punishment for being owned by the
russian government uh the the justice
department tried to essentially to take
us off the air and there there really
wasn't a legal way to do it so what they
did is
uh they approached all of the platforms
that carried our our show
i'm talking about itunes i heart radio
spreaker spotify tune in youtube
between all of those
those uh platforms
we had between 35 000 and 38 000
listeners a day
we were dropped by all of them
and so all we have left now is
just the terrestrial signal
and rumble which is a relatively new
platform we have
if if we're lucky on a good day
we'll have 500 downloads so we've gone
from 38 000 to 500 nobody listens to our
station
and that's because that's the way the
justice department wants it yeah but
they still keep the illusion
diversity and freedom exactly
because they can say well look the
russians still have a radio station a
propaganda station in in washington and
i'll tell you another thing the
washington post took a real swipe at me
the other day um every thursday i have a
segment called criminal injustice where
i've got another journalist kevin
gastala who i like and respect very very
much and paul wright who runs an
organization called the human rights
defense center and he's also the
publisher of prison legal news and
criminal legal news magazines
outstanding magazines for the industry
so we have this show 30 minutes every
thursday and we talk about
prison conditions and prison reform and
sentencing reform and crooked
prosecutors and judges on the take and
things like that
that the mainstream media mostly ignore
and the washington post had a reporter
listen to the show the other day
and she said that
by highlighting these problems in the
american justice system that i am
weakening our democracy
she actually said that i'm weakening our
democracy and if i was a loyal american
i wouldn't discuss these issues on a
russian station
this is a journalist yeah for the
washington was it was it's an opinion
piece or this was supposed to be
this was a reporter an actual reporter
for the washington post
i'm wondering
our democracy well this is the argument
putin would make in russia of anybody
who you know including some outstanding
athletes and so forth who've dared to
criticize is going invading
ukraine you're weakening russia that's
always the argument you know
you're weakening germany we have to
conquer eastern europe i mean come on
but the washington post
does jeff bezos know that
you know but i i do want to i mean i
want to wrap this up but i i want to
we're making light of some things
that are really you know we're talking
here about the possibility of a war that
could end life on the planet yeah and
i'm not talking now just about you know
the issue of the moment of climate
change we're certainly helping with that
nothing that brings that on faster than
you know uh the wastefulness of military
and the destruction of military wars and
so forth and now we need fossil fuel and
coal is coming back and nuclear power
plants
i i actually visited chernobyl a year
after the explosion when it was a very
tight security area and the idea that
now throughout western europe where you
had the green movement and everything it
was so powerful that now you know france
is thrilled with its nuclear power
plants they're modernizing them and
they're bringing back more nuclear power
and so forth but yes so i i don't mean
to minimize obviously
in weeks like this uh uh climate change
but the the irony
is that where previously and i'm an old
guy i've been around a long time so i i
can go back i can remember world war ii
frankly as a kid and so forth i've never
been in a time of such a myopic time
towards the possibility of nuclear war
as now
and i don't get it and you're a guy who
studied all this stuff in graduate
school and then at for the c.i.a
and you know the enemy you were there to
fight different enemies including the
old you know uh
remnants of the old soviet union and so
forth uh
so and well the old soviet union so what
how do you see that there's almost a
giddiness
i i even i i would go further and
insanity but giddiness in the sense of
we just don't take it seriously
you know that that the possibility of
nuclear weapons being used
whether intentionally accident
yes you're absolutely right i heard
something today that at first
excited me and when i heard the rest of
it
depressed me i heard today that the
russians are preparing
a diplomatic offer to the
ukrainians to end the war and it's going
to be what we always thought it would be
when it finally came
that
the russians would
would cease
hostilities
if they can keep
what they took in crimea
and
the two
regions of the donbass luhansk and
donetsk uh are treated as independent
republics under russian control so they
want to keep what they what they've
taken
the donbass and the crimea
and i heard that the americans
have told the ukrainians
absolutely not not under any
circumstances so when you hear these
these jokes that the united states is
prepared to fight to the last ukrainian
uh it's it's actually true
we want the ukrainians to bog the
russians down forever even if it results
in the deaths of every last ukrainian in
that country
we don't have an interest in peace
well that's certainly you're an expert
on the afghan war and that you remember
it's a big new brzezinski
it's the one who bragged about tricking
the russians into going into afghanistan
absolutely to give them their vietnam
and now they have their vietnam and
ukraine but i'm raising a a an even more
concerning question not and not that the
loss of life isn't concerning but there
doesn't seem to be an awareness
of of the power of nuclear
warfighting i mean it's like you're back
you know i remember interviewing ronald
reagan about the possibility of nuclear
warfighting and uh first president bush
before ira what was president and but
there's that old mentality
and what do we think you know let's say
you can push them back against the wall
what we really are at a moment where
people are talking about these as usable
weapons
and we're modernizing our force
and there's the restraint
and it's interesting to have henry
kissinger
uh be a voice of restraint now okay and
kissinger you know after all he was with
nixon when nixon went to negotiate with
what was supposed to be the most brutal
fearsome communist leader ever uh
mouseyton
and and and they did it and they did it
because they thought it would enhance
stability and peace
and and you know now the idea of even
negotiating
uh with putin seems like heresy yes
can't even negotiate and there's no
peace movement there's not one single
member of the us congress liberal
progressive not one single member who
was opposed uh
to to the total uh rearmament of the
ukrainians and spend any whatever money
you got and uh you know and no one's
talking about give peace a chance no no
one's talking about negotiation and i
want to end this but because we were
started out talking about saudi arabia
it seems to me i'm not the first person
to talk about it that there's really a
realignment
of power in the world and it's not
obviously communist or or democratic for
that reason
or the president wouldn't be going to
saudi arabia to get their endorsement
but there is a recognition that there
are people who favor a multi-polar world
yes and people who believe
in u.s leadership because after all for
the europeans now that's what they've
lined up behind yes uh you know this is
not the old days of owner owns and
german social democrats and so forth uh
and on the other hand you've got some
very powerful countries like china and
india
and uh you know brazil maybe and others
uh that are arguing no
uh this is overreach by the u.s
and uh i wonder
what the what the message is from saudi
arabia because part of this multi-polar
world idea
is you know you have the uae and and so
they do business
with these other folks
and in opec they're actually on the same
side
they are on the same side you know it
i i've detected that same shift
especially in saudi arabia and um
you know it's it's
easy for us to sort of rely on history
that well it's always been this one
certain way there's no reason why it
should change now on the contrary i
think it's actually already changed just
a few weeks ago
the chinese announced that they had made
an oil deal with the saudis not unusual
at all what was unusual is that the
saudis agreed to accept payment in
chinese yuan
and that is the first time
the first time that a country ever
bought oil from saudi arabia that wasn't
in dollars
this is exactly what the united states
has worried would happen since the 1970s
is that the dollar would be replaced by
a basket of currencies is what we used
to be worried about and now by the
chinese currency
in oil transactions
so i think the saudis
while they may not be walking away from
us they're exploring other options
that the relationship with the us just
isn't as
critical as it used to be
well also right now we have a deal
between india and russia right for to
buy russian oil that's going to use the
currency of the uae that's right uh as
the standard that that that just
happened in the last few days it's
shocking isn't it well i mean i know
about shocking and uh in the sense that
it's certainly a startling
uh difference but it does threaten the
dominance of the dollar
maybe that's
where we should end it
but it seems to me that that
if we survive this
uh you know the plates have shifted yes
and we're not really i don't know get
the last word from you
but i think that's what happened on this
saudi trip an american president went
there to beg and he came back
empty-handed
i want to add one other thing before we
we end bob um it's easy to
consider
mohammed bin salman as some sort of a
cartoon character villain a villain you
know like from uh rocky and bullwinkle
or something
and
it should be so easy he's actually very
complicated yes i believe he's evil um i
think that's important but then at the
same time
he's actually reforming saudi arabia
and and implementing changes that that
just 10 years ago people wouldn't have
even dreamt of
the thing things like
women driving for example women are now
allowed to
enter movie theaters women have always
been banned from movie theaters in saudi
arabia women are allowed to bowl believe
it or not bowling is very popular in
saudi arabia and now women are allowed
to participate
i saw
at least 50 of the women that i saw on
this trip were unveiled
absolutely unheard of before uh muhammad
bin bin salman became crown prince you
would be beaten with a with a
a cane with a with a wooden cane by a
member of the religious police if you've
been caught without a veil the last time
i was in saudi arabia so things are
changing
i think that was because the americans
were there the american president no not
at all
you can you can see there's been a
societal change
this this wasn't you know temporary and
people just experimenting this is this
is a real change
well you know you make a very important
i mean
i'll extend this a little bit you make a
very important point that any serious
observer of international politics comes
up against
it ain't simple no you know and we
always want to have
a simple view of the enemy and a
simplistic view of the problem
and and what was acknowledged you know
uh nixon going to china first of all
nixon and kissinger were not saints
they were killing people in the millions
uh
in vietnam and
laos and
cambodia
and you know i witnessed a lot of that
uh but they also could be rational they
could have an idea of self-interest that
wasn't destructive
uh and uh
you know mao
obviously
was not saintly he was capable of
encouraging great destruction and
fighting and tension
uh whether it was making a revolution or
it was with the cultural
revolution and now we've got this again
the simple thing putin is nothing more
than a menace or the crown prince of of
saudi arabia
and the whole idea
of
realistic diplomacy used to be
you still can't have a nuclear war
and that all wars are ultimately costly
to everyone and that if you can do it
through diplomacy and negotiation
and in the face of nuclear war you
better do it through diplomacy
negotiation you got to give it a try yes
and and that's what's missing now that's
why i use the word a giddiness there's
sort of a feeling we'll show them and we
can do with it and they're just a
third-rate power well russia has shown
once again they're not a third-rate
power when it comes to the military
they got their deadly toys they can play
witches like we do
and they're not going to be winners and
that the losers or ordinary people will
get their lives
smashed so i'll give you the last
word on this but i i just wonder talking
to people in the press talking to some
people do they understand
the seriousness of the moment
i think they do
and
i i don't fully understand why
the word isn't getting out there i i do
want to add one more thing before we
leave
um
you know i remember when i was at the
cia i had just started at the cia and
the gulf war the first gulf war was just
beginning and i remember just being
shocked every time i would hear someone
on the news say that saddam hussein was
crazy
he's not at all crazy he may have
miscalculated
but
i would compare him to a mob boss to an
organized crime boss rather than to a
crazy person there's no evidence that
he's crazy but you know we've said that
besides saddam being crazy that qaddafi
was crazy osama bin laden was crazy
arafat was crazy everybody that we don't
like is crazy they're not crazy well
even donald trump right the democratic
donald trump
yeah
not crazy
or crazy as a fox that's right
all right let's leave it on that note uh
i want to say john kuriaku i'm
really proud to have you right in
columns thank you so much i'm proud to
be associated with you i've had a lot of
fun
and uh i think the work holds up
and uh but we'll talk uh at another time
uh but i'm sure these issues are gonna
get scarier rather than
saner but okay i want to thank
christopher ho and laura condorgerian uh
the producers at kcrw put these podcasts
on joshua shear our executive producer
natasha kimi zapati who edits and writes
the introduction and the jkw foundation
the memory of a very independent
terrific writer jean stein who helps
fund some of these broadcasts see you
next week with another edition of sheer
intelligence